<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sandesh Pokhrel</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/</link><description>Recent content on Sandesh Pokhrel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Hideous Loop</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/09/a-hideous-loop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/09/a-hideous-loop/</guid><description>Exams.cpp int main(){
while(!EngineeringOver){
for (const auto&amp;amp; exam: semesters){
/* A month-long ordeal that drains the life out of you, makes you and a thousand others monotonic to a mental cycle of three days.
It’s fun and games before the iconic three days begin. Well not exactly fun and games because we are primed for this hammer-blow of a month with project deadlines, assessments and presentations but its trivial compared to the rollercoaster we ride during the exam but the real game begins on T-3 days to exam.</description></item><item><title>Langtang Valley Trek</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/06/langtang-valley-trek/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/06/langtang-valley-trek/</guid><description>Langtang Valley “The name Langtang comes from the Tibetan language, where &amp;lsquo;Lang&amp;rsquo; Yak and &amp;lsquo;Teng&amp;rsquo; mean – to follow.”
Prologue The pandemic had struck hard at everyone, even the most introverted of us were eager to travel and explore. The burning fire of youth in us could only be quenched by a trek that demanded every last bit of effort from us.
In the back of my mind was the thought of having missed Langtang Trek, a few months ago due to the uncertainty of having practical classes in the middle of the vacation.</description></item><item><title>A trip to snowland</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/02/a-trip-to-snowland/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/02/a-trip-to-snowland/</guid><description>A trip to snowland Two bikes, four people and a perfect trip, we sketched down our plan. But as &amp;lsquo;AL Green&amp;rsquo; said, “How can you stop the rain from falling down&amp;hellip;?” It rained cats and dogs on our plan. It turned out to be a blessing in disguise as the company grew to six, hills grew thicker with snow and the weather next day was clearer.
The Facebook group was assembled at 6:00 pm a day before the trip, the official start of a trip these days.</description></item><item><title>Buildup to the Finale</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2021/05/buildup-to-the-finale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2021/05/buildup-to-the-finale/</guid><description>UEFA Champions League Final 2021 It’s here, and we have been here before, but its different. There’s fear for the repeat of 2008 but there’s hope for the 2012 miracle. It’s 2021 and we come to &amp;lsquo;Estadio de Dragao&amp;rsquo; as underdogs. Dread the fight but just enough to not let your arrogance get to you, believe that you can and will triumph on your quest, and live, live the moment like you’ll never live it again because you might just never live it again.</description></item><item><title>Groundhog Day</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2020/05/groundhog-day/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2020/05/groundhog-day/</guid><description>Life during the lockdown Yet another day has come to an end, and like the past two months, I am scratching my head thinking what things I did today were &amp;ldquo;productive&amp;rdquo;. I lay there in my bed recalling the early morning row with my mom because I overslept yet again.
Mom vs me (1-0), if we are keeping scores. It really pissed me off for the first few weeks or so, but I guess, I got used to her rants.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/about/</guid><description>Computer Engineer in the making&amp;hellip;
Games, Football, Books, Mathematics, Movies, Travel, Psychology&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Projects</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/projects/</guid><description>Github link Forgive me for being a bit lazy here, I&amp;rsquo;ll sort it out.</description></item><item><title>Resume</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/resume/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/resume/</guid><description>Primary Information Name: Sandesh Pokhrel Employment Status: Student
College: Pulchowk Campus, IOE
Undergraduate: Bachelor in Computer Engineering (BCT)
Year: Fourth Year, Seventh Semester
Address:
Primary: Pokhara-17, Kaski Secondary: Pulchowk, Lalitpur (current) Permanent: Thuladihi, Syangja Email:
075bct076.sandesh@pcampus.edu.np (college mail) Skills and Experiences Relevant Skills: Programming Languages - prefer to work in Python, C++, and JavaScript.
Web Development
Front End: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, React.
Excellent experience in working with the Linux development environment including system calls and shell scripting.</description></item></channel></rss>