<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Sandesh Pokhrel</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Sandesh Pokhrel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A trip to snowland</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/02/a-trip-to-snowland/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2022/02/a-trip-to-snowland/</guid><description>A trip to snowland Two bikes, four people and a perfect trip, we sketched down our plan. But as &amp;lsquo;AL Green&amp;rsquo; said, “How can you stop the rain from falling down&amp;hellip;?” It rained cats and dogs on our plan. It turned out to be a blessing in disguise as the company grew to six, hills grew thicker with snow and the weather next day was clearer.
The Facebook group was assembled at 6:00 pm a day before the trip, the official start of a trip these days.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-trip-to-snowland">A trip to snowland</h2>
<p>Two bikes, four people and a perfect trip, we sketched down our plan. But as &lsquo;AL Green&rsquo; said, <em>“How can you stop the rain from falling down&hellip;?”</em> It rained cats and dogs on our plan. It turned out to be a blessing in disguise as the company grew to six, hills grew thicker with snow and the weather next day was clearer.</p>
<p>The Facebook group was assembled at 6:00 pm a day before the trip, the official start of a trip these days. We planned our escape at 8:00pm from <em>Hari Chowk</em>. As it usually happens we started the ride at 8:00<em>NST</em> (Nepali Standard Time) thanks to the trash-can Siddhartha Bank calls an ATM, which debited my account and refused to spit out the cash. Who knew that the bank would conspire for my mom to win an argument yet again? Yeah.. she’d mentioned taking cash from home instead of going to the ATM but I trusted technology more than my mother and faced the consequences. Not a great start to the trip but thankfully it wasn’t the sign of things to come.</p>
<p>Kishor Dai and I in <em>FZ</em>, Gaurav Dai and Manish Dai in <em>Xpulse</em>, and Manish Dai and Pramish Vai in <em>Gixxer</em>. A final look at google maps to note-down the number of some of the hotels at Ghorepani. Down jackets, faces covered with masks, woolen hats and goggles off we went… Silky smooth road in Hemja with mountains running abreast us. I was busy filming every moment as we rode past the spotless road and into a typical Nepali highway. As we rode towards Lumle, the weather got more chillier but we were well suited for the cold.</p>
<p>We were famished by the time we stopped for lunch. Manoj dai, who I know from Pulchowk Campus, Gaurav and Kishor dai&rsquo;s classmate, had recently been posted at the ward office in <em>Patichaur</em> and joined us for lunch. Manoj dai sponsored the lunch as a treat for his recent job posting. We had rice with fish curry which was known to be a speciality on the highway. It was the best fish curry I have ever had, and no it&rsquo;s not just hunger speaking, it was genuinely finger licking good. I cannot say the same for the price though.</p>
<p>We turned right from <em>MaalDhunga</em> towards <em>Beni bazaar</em> and it was like we switched to the dark side of the moon. Puddles, right in the middle of the road and the occurrences were multiple. Heavy reconstruction of the &ldquo;highway&rdquo; was going on which led to diversions. Slimy mud mixture, large broken rocks and water canals ruining the already disintegrated highway. A major blockade was a truck loaded with gas cylinders stuck on the muddy road. Even a dozer was unable to pry the truck out. Luckily we had great riders. They expertly navigated from beside the truck and we were off again after a slight delay.</p>
<p>We stopped to regroup on <em>Beni bazaar</em>, miniature under a hanging cliff . Cannot say that none of us were tempted to go rogue and change course when we found out that it was the same road that led to Mustang. The state of the highway though, uff… no wonder Myagdi district is on the list of <em>bikat</em> districts.</p>
<p><em>Next stop Pokhare-bagar.</em></p>
<p>At <em>Pokhare-bagar</em> we stopped for snacks and a short break from the long tiring ride. A casual chat to the locals revealed that we were late on schedule and it might get pitch dark by the time we reached Ghorepani. They also mentioned that the snow in some parts is hip-deep. So we rang Hotel Snowland and booked a package for six.
The road got worse as we ascended. The sun sank and it started to grow dark. The road was still muddy and fractured but it was the snow that created all the problems. Snow on the sides and ice on the road made it impossible to create traction. Our riders got to experience riding a snowmobile at 8pm on a winter night on a road like no other. There were moments when it wasn’t the bike carrying us but the opposite. Skidding and sliding we made our way to the end of the road.</p>
<p>We were still an hour away from the hotel. We moved through the middle of the forest without any idea of where the small slit of foot trails in the snow led. We had to wander around for sometime before we found the right trail on the thick snow. Finally after a long walk, we reached Hotel Snowland. It was about 10pm when we reached the hotel. Soaked in snow we gathered around the hearth to heat ourselves and our clothes for the journey tomorrow.</p>
<p>It was 5:30am when I woke up to <em>Sia&rsquo;s Greatest</em>. No sign of life in the room as our tired souls were in a state of deep sleep. Full of energy and determined not to miss the sunrise I climbed out of my bed and was ready in a minute. I started waking everyone up but some of us were too tired to walk in the snow again. So it was just half of the company that left at 6:15am to Poonhill. The estimated time for sunrise was 7:00am. With the clock ticking we set off in the snow.</p>
<p>The morning glow was mesmerizing. We were late and were possibly going to miss the sunrise but the view was one to die for. We couldn&rsquo;t wait till the top to capture those moments so we started posing here and there, adding to our delay. A sea of golden red above a silver lake and us floating in it. The first rays of sunlight on the peak of Annapurna South stirred my emotions. I summoned all my might and started running towards the hill, yes run. Panting, clambering, slipping, on all fours but not stopping.</p>
<p>We reached the top just as the sun was shying away from the hill that hid it from us. Golden hill, silver lake and crystal white mountains. Ohh, did I let that view sink in. It was then time to let the floodgates open. We went about clicking pictures left, right and center. Acrobatics in the snow, casual poses, dancing, jumping, sleeping, diving, trust falls, cool-dude, and whatnot cause who knows if I will ever be there again. Never had I ever taken so many pictures.</p>
<p>You can never have your fill with mountains but you must depart nonetheless. We started our descent after enough time at the top. The hills below seemed to be afloat in a lake of clouds, the trees shaking off the snow stuck in their branches and the clouds rising up to meet the mountain peaks. We slipped and slid our way back to the hotel.</p>
<p>Breakfast beckoned at the hotel. The journey home began soon after. A click of our company of seven, six of us and a snowman as a final souvenir. Vlogging, skidding and dancing in the knee deep snow, we got back to Chitre where we had parked our bikes overnight.</p>
<p>The sun had melted away a few layers of snow. The meltwater flowed down the road adding to the mud and puddles. Better mud than snow for us bikers. We descended slowly on our bikes, ever so careful of the pitfalls of a rural road. We had come unscathed from the toughest part of the highway, but Galeshwor Mahadev had planned a different end to our journey.</p>
<p>Near Galeshwor, one of our bike’s roller chains broke. We had to push the bike to <em>Beni bazaar</em> for repair. An additional time cost was added to our plans, and by the time we left Beni for Pokhara it was already 7pm. We rode slowly on the pitch dark and empty highway. The visibility was also diminished by thick mist through which you could barely see. Cold that burned like a steel knife pierced through our trousers as we made our way back home at 11.</p>
<p>Like every travel story it was lively, engrossing and memorable. The story is never complete without a bit of setback. On an ending note I’d like to add from this experience; little snow is dear, a little more is loved and too much is an avalanche but damn did we enjoy the avalanche.</p>
<h3 id="psst">Psst&hellip;</h3>
<p><em>NST - Nepali Standard Time, usually an hour or two late from the promised time.</em><br>
<em>Bikat - underdeveloped</em><br>
<em>FZ, Xpulse, Gixxer - bikes</em></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Buildup to the Finale</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2021/05/buildup-to-the-finale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2021/05/buildup-to-the-finale/</guid><description>UEFA Champions League Final 2021 It’s here, and we have been here before, but its different. There’s fear for the repeat of 2008 but there’s hope for the 2012 miracle. It’s 2021 and we come to &amp;lsquo;Estadio de Dragao&amp;rsquo; as underdogs. Dread the fight but just enough to not let your arrogance get to you, believe that you can and will triumph on your quest, and live, live the moment like you’ll never live it again because you might just never live it again.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="uefa-champions-league-final-2021">UEFA Champions League Final 2021</h2>
<p>It’s here, and we have been here before, but its different. There’s fear for the repeat of 2008 but there’s hope for the 2012 miracle. It’s 2021 and we come to &lsquo;Estadio de Dragao&rsquo; as underdogs. Dread the fight but just enough to not let your arrogance get to you, believe that you can and will triumph on your quest, and live, live the moment like you’ll never live it again because you might just never live it again.</p>
<h3 id="t--18-hours">T- 18 hours</h3>
<p>It’s the 90th minute of the match and Chelsea are a goal down. Everyone&rsquo;s eyes are on the clock. The rythmic heart-beats getting more intense. Panting, they jostle for every loose ball. Hands in face, praying, begging to anyone who is listening, shouting at the screen like you are there on the pitch.</p>
<p>A golden opportunity for Chelsea comes by…. and ….GOALLL….. its 1-1. But wait…. obscurity, the picture&rsquo;s getting blurr, and it seems like its Crystal Palace who’ve scored and its against Barcelona…. Did your excitement just switch teams. What’s going on&hellip; the game began as a match between Manchester City and Chelsea the Champions League Final&hellip; , what’s the scoreline in Chelsea’s game…., oh shoot did I fall asleep during the game. You start gaining consciousness and things slowly start to sink in.</p>
<p>Its Match-Day. You want to take a sigh of relief and reflect on that weird dream. They have been getting weirder each passing day as the final edges closer. Nervousness is an understatement for what football fans feel before a game starting as underdogs, specially when its ‘the’ Final. Your mind is fixated on that one prize. You cannot concentrate on any task. Everything and anything reminds you of the game to come in about 18-hours. Flashbacks and discussions are all you want to do all day until kickoff.  You’ve even started becoming superstitious start to feel as if whatever you do or do not do might have an effect on the game to come. You are weak on your knees, a spectator from far away, imagine what the player’s are going through.</p>
<h3 id="t-12-hours">T-12 hours</h3>
<p>The players are taking a walk around the city and you are following the action in Porto from your living room every minute as fans gather around the ‘Estadio de Dragao’. Tactics talks and line-up predictions begin but we are all too superstitious to predict the final score, having seen that when we make predictions before a game it ends up in defeat. Pep, the genius, what has he got planned to decimate us or what Tuchel has up his sleeve this time to make three in a row against the genius. Talks go on about Pep having won all the finals he’s played since 2011, and has lost only one in 12 finals. On the other side he’s never beaten Chelsea in the Champions league playing 3 games 2 draws and a loss. History suggesting no first time finalist has won the CL, and so on as facts begin to come to light with the main event edging closer.</p>
<h3 id="t-1-and-a-half-hour">T-1 and a half hour</h3>
<p>The lineups drop, half an hour earlier than in any other game. Chelsea’s lineup as expected Mendy in goal, Azpilicueta©, Silva, Rudiger, James, Kante, Jorginho, Chilwell, Mount, Werner, Havertz. A strong team on paper, players in good form and possibly the best team we could have hoped for. Then comes City’s lineup : Ederson, Walker, Stones, Dias, Zinchenko, Gundogan, Foden, B.Silva, Sterling, De-bruyne, Mahrez. You look at their lineup again and realize there’s no DM(Defensive Midfielder). Everyone goes crazy half of them saying Pep’s made a blunder starting the final without a DM and and the other half saying more attacking players, we’re going to get decimated. And discussions begin yet again. Who might score? Who is going to rise to the occasion? Who’s going to fight for that inch? Who’s gonna have the guts to take the last penalty if it goes to penalties?</p>
<h3 id="kickoff">Kickoff</h3>
<p>A tight tense game kicked off and fans were biting their nails from the very beginning. Manchester City as always cool composed on the ball as Chelsea formed a defensive block which had been nearly impenetrable since Tuchel arrived. Touch tight passing, fans cheering and players giving it their all made for a great cup final. Chelsea dangerous on the break, City patient and probing…
Clock ticks to the 42nd minute of the game with the ball at the Mendy’s feet. A long ball to the left is flicked first time by Ben Chilwell to the rushing Mason Mount. Mount turns. Timo Werner draggs the center back away from the center creating a passing lane for Mount to play Havertz in on goal.
Ederson rushes.. Kai gets there first.. ball bounces off the keeper and Kai has an empty net infront of him. GOALLL…… The most expensive player in Chelsea Football Club’s history repays the 90 million quid with a kick of the ball. The half-time score</p>
<pre><code>    Chelsea 1-0 Manchester City.  
</code></pre>
<p>The players come in for the second half. Another half of stand your ground and fight for Chelsea as for City a show of their character. The Champions of England need to push further to get the European Crown. The game progressed and the belief among the Chelsea fans and players seemed to be ever more rising. Crunching tackles, fearsome, resolute and dogged Chelsea were impenetrable to the free flowing and slick football of Manchester City.</p>
<p>94th minute on the clock and still Chelsea hold the slender lead. It falls to the feet of Riyad Mahrez, just outside the box from a throw-in… and MAHREZZ…. Flashbacks run through the minds of Chelsea fans, that John Terry miss, the moment Chelsea fans covered their eyes in horror to an Andreas Iniesta equalizer in injury time, all rushing through our minds as the ball slowly floated towards the net.<br>
Agonizingly close but the ball doesn’t strike the back of the net this time.</p>
<h3 id="full-time">Full-Time</h3>
<p><strong>THEY HAVE DONE IT AGAIN. EUROPEAN CHAMPIONS AFTER 9 YEARS.
ECSTASY  FOR CHELSEA AT THE EXPENSE OF MANCHESTER CITY’S HEARTBREAK.</strong></p>
<p>The European Dream not to be for Pep Guardiola. Thomas Tuchel, finally gets his hands on the trophy which he missed by a whisker last season. The Chelsea fans rejoice singing,
<em>“We’ve got Super Tommy Tuchel and he knows exactly what we need! Thiago in the back Timo in attack, Chelsea gonna win the Champions League.”</em>  and I join in the chant from my living room.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Groundhog Day</title><link>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2020/05/groundhog-day/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sandesh-pokhrel.com.np/posts/2020/05/groundhog-day/</guid><description>Life during the lockdown Yet another day has come to an end, and like the past two months, I am scratching my head thinking what things I did today were &amp;ldquo;productive&amp;rdquo;. I lay there in my bed recalling the early morning row with my mom because I overslept yet again.
Mom vs me (1-0), if we are keeping scores. It really pissed me off for the first few weeks or so, but I guess, I got used to her rants.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="life-during-the-lockdown">Life during the lockdown</h2>
<p>Yet another day has come to an end, and like the past two months, I am scratching my head thinking what things I did today were &ldquo;productive&rdquo;.
I lay there in my bed recalling the early morning row with my mom because I overslept yet again.</p>
<pre><code>Mom vs me (1-0), if we are keeping scores. 
</code></pre>
<p>It really pissed me off for the first few weeks or so, but I guess, I got used to her rants.</p>
<p>Definitely not a good start to the day. Popping a <em>pantop</em>, I sat there waiting for that <em>not so early</em> morning acidity to go away. Mom walks in with a plate of sliced beetroot, carrots, apples and a glass of lukewarm water preaching about what some Facebook post said about the benefits of lukewarm water in an empty stomach.</p>
<p>The row we had forgotten about over a loving plate of fruits. I didn&rsquo;t like the taste of beetroot when I first tried it, a month ago but now it had really grown onto me. The muddy smell it gave used to be worse a month ago as I recall. Now, even the red tint it leaves on the whites I always wear doesn&rsquo;t seem to bother me.</p>
<p>Just when the plate is empty, the fruits had done their job, and I found myself rushing for the washroom.
Scrolling through the social media feeds as I clear my bowels, I stumble upon news that your rival’s transfers aren&rsquo;t working out while your club is busy swooping in <em>generational</em> players.</p>
<p>Half an hour or so of reading the book you were so into and it is lunchtime. I eat whatever mom has prepared for lunch, facetiously complaining that she&rsquo;s put too much besar in the curry. She gives me a look that reads, ‘You ought to have prepared whatever you liked insted of sleeping till noon.&rsquo; and adds that Mr. Prime Minister has said it helps fight covid.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t bother explaining and getting into an argument again, so I just finish my meal and get up. Finally, I turn on my laptop, <em>rubbing my palms</em>, let&rsquo;s get to work, but wait&hellip; what am I supposed to do today? Like I had done anything yesterday. Checking a list of items, I have in my to-do list:</p>
<pre><code>Skyrim (FYI the best game ever)  
GTA IV  
Humble Pi (continue the book)  
Python / JS / C++ / other random stuff to learn  
A list of movies/series friends recommended  
A list of videos I bookmarked yesterday  
A bunch of papers/resources to read from  
</code></pre>
<p>As I&rsquo;m deciding what I want to do for the day, BAM!! Social media takes over!</p>
<pre><code>Social media vs me (67-2).
</code></pre>
<p>(Damn it’s gonna be a tough comeback, social media’s rather good at this.) Almost two hours flies by surfing between Twitter, Facebook, Instagram, Discord and engaging in anything you find there.</p>
<p>And when friends in group chat start talking about stuff but you can&rsquo;t make out if its Sumerian or ancient Egyptian they are talking, you slap yourself into &ldquo;productivity&rdquo; and decide to continue the fractal (Koch curve) in JavaScript and get to work.</p>
<p>The only bit of code you&rsquo;ve managed today is ctx.draw( ), because without realizing you have started surfing on the internet which began from the search about <em>vertices of a triangle</em>.</p>
<p>Not even an hour has passed before your butt cheeks are weary and your tummy rumbles. It’s about 3:30 when you can no longer bear the rumble of your tummy and call out to your mom for khaja, but she is nowhere to be found.</p>
<p>I could sense her in our neighbors’ house complaining about the lousy son who wakes up late and doesn&rsquo;t help her with chores. Corona or no, aunties got to chat.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s give her something good to talk about for tomorrow then. I <em>dramatically</em> enter the kitchen as I imagine myself in a chef’s clothes.
Poor man&rsquo;s Gordon Ramsay mode <em>activated</em>. Watching too much Gordon Ramsay videos might not make you a good chef, but one thing&rsquo;s for sure, you&rsquo;ll narrate the ingredients in your head as  he does:</p>
<pre><code>A fistful of spaghetti
Into boiling water (10 minutes wait, for it to be just the right texture)
Into the colander
A touch of olive oil 
        (that's what you say but you are pouring just a bit of *tori ko tel* 
        into the colander terrified your mom 
        would haunt you for pouring half a bottle of it for a fistful of spaghetti)
Pan. Heat. Oil.
Fry chopped tomato, garlic and onion. Blend.
Spaghetti into the plate; spread some grated cheese and the blended sauce.
</code></pre>
<p>“Voila!”</p>
<pre><code> Some other day's spaghetti
</code></pre>
<p><img src="/img/spaghetti.png" alt="(Some other day; a different version)"></p>
<p>The dish is ready and mom arrives to an aromatic smell of cheese and garlic in the kitchen. Her eyes meet mine; wild west theme plays in the background, and she starts yelling at me about the state of the kitchen. I had made lassi topped with peanuts while waiting for the spaghetti to boil.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bon apatite, mademoiselle&rdquo;<br>
I serve her the dish with a glass of lassi. She runs her eyes over the neatly placed dish to find any missing ingredients. Ah ha! You forgot besar.</p>
<p>“What good is chowmein without besar?”
“And for the last time it’s not chowmein its spaghetti <em>Italian hand gesture</em>, just try, and tell me if is it any good?”</p>
<p>Her fork rolls and gathers a bunch of spaghetti strands, cheese and the sauce.</p>
<p>She tastes, <em>Anton Ego</em> style.<br>
“It’s actually good!”</p>
<pre><code>Mom vs me (1-1). Sweet equalizer, well tasty to be more precise.
</code></pre>
<p>Well, let’s continue the code and finish off the Koch curve.<br>
A few moments later,<br>
<em>Epic Saxo Guy rings under the pillow</em><br>
I pick up.<br>
“It’s almost five, you ready to go.”<br>
That cooking maneuver just took me an hour and half. Damn you, Gordon Ramsay. Gordon Ramsay inside me replies, as he usually does, in a cursed tone.</p>
<p>I didn’t really want to go running then, so I replied
“Well, I am kinda doing some coding, let’s skip for today”.</p>
<p>“You said that yesterday. Now get ready, I’ll be there in 5 minutes.”</p>
<p>Reluctantly, I change into my running shorts and shoes. But, changing into these gets me runner’s high and I start sprinting until my lungs can no longer handle. (Its lockdown, I know.
I wore a mask and maintained distance).</p>
<p>We’re running, striking up conversations and he mentions that he was hitting on some unknown girls and he started flirting with one of them. But the girl turned out to be a cousin of his classmate, and now he was embarrassed. Good for you, you can at least have a chat, I thought. I can’t even seem to have a conversation with anyone.</p>
<p>A bunch of guys are flexing their rock-hard abs in the park. I put my hands on my belly and sigh as we go by.<br>
Soaked from head to toe, I return home, cool down and take a shower. I get back to the code and polish it for a while, and before long, it’s dinner time.</p>
<p>Casual table talks commence. All of a sudden, mom and me are arguing about the number of Covid cases today.
Unlike any other time, I was confident, and I placed a bet to do the dishes if she’s correct.
Dad throws in his say and mom hers. For all the BBC radio news mom listens to and the Routiney dai ko post I follow, neither of us were correct.</p>
<p>Dad <em>R.K.O’ed</em> us out of nowhere, and the final score now reads 2-1-1. I picked washing dishes over cleaning the kitchen. When we were done eating, I muffed my ears with my headphones and listened to Roy Dotrice narrate Ser Ilyn Payne lopping off Ned Starks head.<br>
Doing the dishes feels like a backdrop when you’re fully into the audiobook.</p>
<p><em>Back to the code.</em><br>
A semicolon here, a bool there and it seemed like it was over. But alas! The canvas looked like a 3-year-old going nuts on a sketchpad before the browser crashed.</p>
<p>Ten tutorials and forty Stack Overflow questions later, I found the bug was a negative sign missing while calculating the coordinates. Frustrated with myself for making such a silly mistake, I now had a strong urge to take it out on somebody.</p>
<p>Loading up seems to take forever in this dang old PC, but the music makes the wait bearable.
Kazin Niko starts firing and taking people’s limbs off with a Bazooka. When I’d had my fill from the bloodbath, it was bedtime, and I laid down scratching my head.</p>
<p>In terms of productivity we had none today - so tuck yourself into bed, “hoping” to wake up early and put an end to that self-similar recursive piece of geometry.</p>
<h3 id="understanding-my-language">Understanding my language</h3>
<p><em>Pantop</em> – a medicine for gastritis<br>
<em>Kazin</em> – Cousin, in thick Eastern European accent, as pronounced in the game<br>
<em>Anton Ego</em> – The food critic in movie Ratatouille<br>
<em>Tori ko tel</em> – mustard oil<br>
<em>R.K.O’ed</em> – wrestling reference</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>